Ritsuko.
（鉄平(てっぺい)）律子(りつこ)
お前の雛見沢(ひなみざわ)の旦那 どうなんね？
How's your husband
in Hinamizawa?
How much do you think
you can squeeze out of him?
どのくらい搾れそうなんよ？
（ﾘﾅ）それがさ…
Listen to this.
別れた奥さんが だいぶ
慰謝料をくれたらしいってのは―
I heard his ex-wife paid him
a lot of consolation money...
聞いてたんだけど
So how'll you lure him in?
どう持ってくつもりなんよ？
I'll use you and have him pay
in order to end my ties with you.
（ﾘﾅ）あんたをダシに
手切れ金が要るって持ってくつもり
- "Atonement" Chapter -
Episode 02: PLACE TO RETURN
When They Cry
Behind where I looked back
(who's there in the front)?
I raised my nails in the dark
(and slashed the night).
Raindrops become droplets of
blood and drip down the throat.
If you don't have
a place to go back to...
...then stop here on my finger.
I'll take you away
along with that finger.
To the unopenable
forest where cicadas cry.
You can't turn back anymore.
An emergency came up, so
I'm going out. No dinner. - Dad
He buys me anything
I want. Anything.
（ﾘﾅ）
何でも買ってくれるのよ 何でも
（圭一(けいいち)）
いやぁ 平和すぎて退屈だぜ
Man, it's so boring when
everything is peaceful.
Really?
（ﾚﾅ）そうかな？
レナは平和で退屈なの 好きだよ
I like it when
it's calm and peaceful.
（圭一）レナは
日々が幸せそうで いいよなぁ
You're lucky because every
day seems so happy for you.
（魅音(みおん)）ハハッ… そんなの
羨ましがられても困るよね
It's not too exciting
to be envious of that, huh?
If there's a trick to changing
a boring day into a fun day...
日々の退屈を幸せに
過ごすコツがあるなら教えてくれよ
...I'd like to know.
そんなの簡単だよ
気づくだけだもん
That's easy.
You just have to notice it.
（圭一）気づくって？
Notice what?
That there's a limit to happy days.
（ﾚﾅ）
幸せな日々が有限であることに
It's no use.
（魅音）ム～リムリ！
Kei-chan won't
understand your philosophy.
圭ちゃんにレナの哲学は
通用しないって ねっ？
Right?
Hey, don't treat me like
an insensitive barbarian!
あっ！ 人を
デリカシーのかけらも持たん―
野蛮人扱いするな！
（魅音）ウワッ… ミスター野蛮人
Hey, Mr. Barbarian!
That's right.
そうだよ…
幸せな日々は有限なんだよね
Happy days are limited.
Oh?
Welcome home, Reina-chan.
（ﾘﾅ）あら おかえり 礼奈(れいな)ちゃん
（ﾚﾅ）こんにちは
Hi.
For lunch today,
your father and I...
（ﾘﾅ）今日のお昼にね
お父さんと一緒に―
キーマカレーが とっても
おいしいお店に行ってきたのよ
...went to a restaurant that
had delicious keema curry.
それで
レトルトをお土産に買ってきたの
I brought back some premade
ones, so try them later, okay?
あとで食べてみてね おいしいから
They're good.
I'm looking forward to it.
Thank you very much.
それは楽しみです
ありがとうございます
それでね 礼奈ちゃん
By the way, Reina-chan.
I want to have a talk
with the three of us.
ちょっと
３人で お話ししたいんだけど…
I'm sorry.
（ﾚﾅ）ごめんなさい
（ﾘﾅ）えっ？
I have a friend waiting,
so I'm going out.
ちょっと 友達を待たせてるんで
出かけてきますね
あら またゴミ山で宝探し？
Oh? Another treasure
hunt at the dump?
Should I come next time?
私も今度 行ってみようかしら…
（ﾚﾅ）失礼しま～す
See you later.
Reina-chan!
（ﾘﾅ）礼奈ちゃん！
リナさん…
Rina-san?
礼奈ちゃん 結構 耳遠いほう？
（ﾚﾅ）すみません
Reina-chan, could it be
you're hard of hearing?
I'm sorry.
Are you alone?
Where's your friend?
１人？ お友達は？
（ﾘﾅ）１人で遊んでますよ
I'm playing by myself.
ふ～ん…
その年で なかなか渋いわね
That's quite
interesting for your age.
Bye!
さよなら！
（ﾘﾅ）もう…
Jeez.
（ﾘﾅ）へえ！ ちょっとステキよね
秘密基地みたい
Hey...
It seems interesting.
It seems like a secret place.
ウフフッ…
私だけの秘密の隠れ家(が)なんですよ
It's my own secret place.
ここは誰も来ないし…
No one comes here.
Nor can anyone hear anything.
誰にも何も聞こえません
It's your secret hideout?
（ﾘﾅ）
礼奈ちゃんだけの秘密の隠れ家
アハハハッ… うれしいわねえ
そんな場所に来られるなんて
I'm happy that
I was able to come here.
Reina-chan, there's something
I've been wanting to ask you.
礼奈ちゃんに 前から
聞きたいことがあったんだけどな
（ﾚﾅ）何でしょう？
What is it?
礼奈ちゃん 私のこと好き？
Reina-chan, do you like me?
ウフフッ… 何ですか？ 突然
What do you mean
all of a sudden?
You see...
私ね あなたのお父さんと
おつきあいしてるじゃない
I'm going out
with your dad, right?
（ﾘﾅ）それでね
いろいろと話し合ったのよ
And we've seriously
talked about many things...
...such as our lives
starting now and other things.
これからのことを真剣に
（ﾘﾅ）
これからの生活や いろいろ…
（ﾚﾅの母）
礼奈もアキヒトおじさんのこと―
Reina, you also like
Akihito, don't you?
好きでしょう？
（ﾚﾅ）うん？
（母）それでね お母さん…
And so Mommy...
再婚なんて許さないです
I won't approve remarriage.
えっ？
（ﾚﾅ）お父さんと―
I don't care what relationship
you have with Dad.
どういう つきあい方をしたって
かまいませんが
再婚なんて許さないです
I will not approve remarriage.
ア… アハハハッ！
拒絶もあるかなとは思ってたけど
I thought there
might be some rejection...
ここまで はっきり言われるとは
思わなかったわ
...but I didn't expect you
to be this straightforward.
私が拒絶していたのに
気づいていたのは意外でした
I'm surprised you were aware
of the fact I would reject it.
It was obvious.
そんなの分かるでしょう
Whenever our eyes met,
you immediately ran away.
あんた 私と目を合わせると
すぐ逃げるもん
For my information, tell me.
What don't you like about me?
後学のために教えてよ
私の どこが
気に入らなかったのかしら？
Everything from the start.
最初っから全部
化粧も服も匂いも嫌い
Your makeup,
your clothes, even your smell.
そりゃ好都合だね
私も あんたのこと嫌いだったから
Well, how convenient.
I hated you too, so we're even.
お互いさまよね アハハハッ…
ナメんな クソガキ！
ガタガタ言わされてえか！
Don't mess with me, brat.
You want to get beat up?
Never come to my house again.
二度と家へ来ないでください
再婚なんて 私が絶対に許さない
I will never approve remarriage.
If you want your dad to give up on
remarriage, try to persuade him.
あんたが お父さんに再婚を
断念させたきゃ してごらんって
そんなの今更 意味ないし
That's pointless now.
I am pregnant.
私ね 妊娠してるの
（母）お母さんね…
（ﾚﾅ）うん？
Mommy...
...is pregnant.
（母）妊娠してるの
ウソだ！
Liar!
アッ… ウソじゃないわよ
It's not a lie.
It's the truth.
（ﾘﾅ）本当よ
I heard what you and that man
called Teppei said at the cafe.
（ﾚﾅ）私は聞いてるんだ
お前と鉄平という男が
喫茶店で話しているところを！
お父さんを
“雛見沢の旦那”って呼んで―
I know you call my dad
your Hinamizawa husband...
カモにしようとしていることを
知っている！
...and you're trying
to live off of him!
美人局(つつもたせ)だってことも
全部 知ってるんだ！
And I know all
about the badger game!
ふ～ん… 全部 知ってるんだ？
So you do know everything.
（ﾘﾅ）ここってさ
秘密の隠れ家なんでしょう？
This is your secret hideout, right?
It's a place that no one
knows about, right?
誰も知らない秘密の
場所なんでしょう？
クソガキ ナメやがってよ！
You brat.
How dare you mess with me.
（ﾘﾅ）もうちょいで
ウン千万って金が転がり込むんだよ
In a bit, several million yen
is coming into my hands.
くんだらねえとこで
まどろっこしい！
You are so in the way!
死にさらせや！
Die!
（ﾘﾅ）
殺しは したかなかったんだけどね
I didn't want to kill you.
But I bet I'll never find
a mark like him again.
二度と こんな うまいカモに
会えないだろうしさ！
I planned to disappear
as soon as I got his money.
どうせ 金巻き上げたら
蒸発するつもりだったしさ
（ﾘﾅ）ウウッ… ちくしょう アア…
ハァ… ハァ…
あっ！ ちょ… ちょっと それ―
W-Wait!
シャレになんない！
That's not funny!
死ね！ 死ね！
（殴る音）
Die!
死んでしまえー！
（殴る音）
Die!
（ﾚﾅ）ハァ… ハァ…
You bastards!
（鉄平）このダラズが！
（鉄平）
人の女に手ぇ出しおって
How dare you touch my woman.
Don't think you can
get away with this!
ただで済むと
思っとるんけ？
So I'm gonna come by tomorrow.
（鉄平）
ええな？ また あした来るけん
ちゃっきり耳そろえて用意しとけや
（蹴る音）
You'd better have all of it ready!
（ツバを吐く音）
ウワッ…
（ﾚﾅ）待ってください！
Please wait!
ああ？ 何じゃ？ おどれは
Who are you?
あ… あの… 私 竜宮(りゅうぐう)の娘ですけど
Um, I'm Ryugu's daughter.
何ね？
What?
Actually, Rina-san
told me to take you to her.
実は
リナさんに 鉄平さんが来たら―
連れてきてほしいって
言われてるんです
ああ？ 律子のヤツ どうしたんね？
What happened to Ritsuko?
She said she has
something to tell you.
何か お話があるとか…
About what?
（鉄平）何ね？ なんで
こんなとこに律子がおるんよ？
Why would Ritsuko be here?
She said she really
wanted to talk alone.
（ﾚﾅ）どうしても
２人っきりで お話がしたいとか…
So...
（ﾚﾅ）それで…
（鉄平）ケッ！
あのボケ なに考えとんじゃ！
Damn, what is that fool thinking?
Huh?
（ﾚﾅ）あれ？
I'm sorry.
（ﾚﾅ）ごめんなさい
電池の接触不良かな？
The light might be out.
ちょっと待ってくださいね
（鉄平）おお 早(は)ようせんね
Please wait a second.
Sure.
Hurry up.
ああ ライターがあるわ
Oh, I have a lighter.
うん？ どこ行ったんね？
Where'd she go?
（たたき割る音）
（鉄平）ウワッ！
When They Cry
（ﾚﾅ）魅ぃちゃん ごめん
Mi-chan, I'm sorry.
I have things to take
care of again today...
ちょっと 今日も用事があって
すぐ帰らないといけないの
...so I gotta go home right away.
えっ？ そうなの？
Really?
What, Rena?
You're going home?
何だよ レナ… 帰っちゃうのかよ？
Oh?
（沙都子(さとこ)）あら…
圭一さんのブザマな
負けっぷりを見れないとは―
It's too bad you can't see
Keiichi-san lose pathetically.
お気の毒ですわ
（梨花(りか)）残念なのです
How regretful.
うん ごめんね
I'm sorry.
昨日も家の用事だったじゃねえかよ
何かあったのか？
You had home
stuff yesterday too.
Did something happen?
アア… ちょっとね いろいろ…
Little things.
What's going on here?
We're missing a lot of pieces.
（圭一）何だ何だ？
随分 足りないじゃないか
（魅音）
これじゃ マージャンはムリだね
We can't play
mah-jongg with this.
What shall we do?
Any suggestions?
どうする？ 何か提案ある人？
（沙都子）
なくなったマージャン牌(パイ)の―
How about treasure hunting for
the missing mah-jongg pieces?
宝探しっていうのは どうですの？
That doesn't sound too exciting.
な～んかパッとしないなぁ
How about doing a more
hard-core treasure hunt?
ほんじゃさ もうちょっと
でっかく宝探しをしてみない？
Treasure hunt?
宝探し？
そう！
宝探しといえば レナのお家芸
Yup, when it comes to treasure
hunting, Rena's the expert.
So the dam dump site, right?
…てことは
ダム現場のゴミ山ですわね
We shouldn't go there because
it's been said that a ghost...
あそこは バラバラ殺人事件の
幽霊が出るから―
近寄らないほうがよいのですよ
...from the dismembered
corpse case appears.
確か バラバラ殺人があって
主犯が いまだ逃走中
You're referring to how the main
suspect is still on the run...
そいつの隠した腕１本が―
...and how the arm that he hid
hasn't been found yet, right?
まだ
見つかってないとかいうやつだろう
ダム戦争のあとに―
Rena's the only one who'd want
to go there after the dam incident.
好きで あそこに
出入りしてるのはレナくらいだよ
All right. Let's go treasure
hunting at the dump today.
よし！ んじゃ
今日はゴミ山の宝探しにしよう
If you find the ghost, you win.
幽霊を見つけられたら 優勝！
次点は隠された右腕！
The hidden right arm, runner-up.
The next will be
something Rena will like.
（魅音）その次は
レナが気に入りそうな何かだね
レナに見せて
白黒つけてもらうってので どう？
How about leaving
the judgment up to Rena?
We agree!
（圭一･沙都子）賛成！
（梨花）なのですよ！
Me too!
（ﾚﾅ）これで全部かな
I think this is all.
（ﾚﾅ）さっきまでね
谷河内(やごうち)のほうに行ってたの
I was just near the river banks...
袋を埋める場所を探しに…
...looking for a place
to bury these bags.
ウフフッ… なかなか
いい場所が見つからなくて
I couldn't find a good place.
（圭一）レナ
（ﾚﾅ）うん？
Rena...
Why?
どうして… どうして
相談してくれなかったんだよ？
Why didn't you consult us?
相談？
（圭一）そうだよ
- Consult you?
- That's right.
俺たちは仲間だろう
We're friends, aren't we?
Friends will be on your
side no matter what.
仲間ってのは 何があっても
無条件で味方になってくれる―
家族同然の存在じゃないのかよ？
We're like a family, aren't we?
俺たちに相談してくれれば
何か力になれたかもしれない
If you consulted us,
we might've been able to help.
そうすれば レナは―
If you did, then you might've
not had to kill someone.
人殺しなど
せずに済んだのかもしれない
Fine then.
（ﾚﾅ）じゃ いいよ
（圭一）うん？
As you said...
（ﾚﾅ）圭一君の言うとおり
私が みんなに―
...let's say I told you guys
about that woman and my father.
お父さんと あの女のことを
打ち明けたとしよう
Now what'll you do?
（ﾚﾅ）さあ どうしてくれるの？
First...
まずは… う～ん…
“まずは” なに？
What?
It's impossible.
ムリだよ　圭一君には何もできない
You can't do anything.
The same goes
for everyone else.
（ﾚﾅ）みんなだって そう
何もできないよ
T-That's...
（圭一）そ… それは…
（ﾚﾅ）仲間なんて―
Friends are only people you hang
out with to do fun and silly things.
楽しくて どうでもいい時間を
一緒に過ごすだけのお友達
They won't be on your side
when painful times come.
本当に つらいときは
味方になってくれないんだよ
そんなこと…
（ﾚﾅ）昔から そうだったよ
That's not...
It's been like that for a while.
It was like that at
the place I came from.
引っ越し先でも そうだったからね
だから 私―
That's why I stopped
disclosing things to my friends.
仲間に打ち明けるのなんか
やめようって思った
だって
どうせ誰も助けてくれないし…
Because no one is going to help.
No one can help.
助けられないもの
（圭一）なんでだよ？
（ﾚﾅ）えっ？
Why?
Why won't you trust us?
なんで信じてくれないんだよ？
圭ちゃん…
Kei-chan...
Even if you told us...
確かに 相談されても
レナの思ってるような―
...we might not be able to come
up with the best idea or solution.
最善の考えも方法も
思いつかないかもしれない
But even so...
でも… それでも…
I believe we could've reached
a better future than now.
きっと 今よりも よりよい未来へ
たどりつけたと信じてる！
A better future than now?
“今よりも よりよい未来”？
そんなの ないよ
There is no such thing.
This is...
これが… これが最善の未来だよ
（圭一）ウソだ！
This is the best future.
Liar!
To prove that,
you've been crying all this time!
だって その証拠に レナは
さっきから泣いてるじゃないか！
はぁ？ 誰が？ 私が？
いつ 涙を流したの？
Who?
Me?
When did I shed tears?
今だよ
ずっと流してるじゃないか！
Right now.
You've been crying.
えっ？
（圭一）自分で分かってないのか？
Don't you notice it?
What you did is the worst thing.
（圭一）レナのやったことは最悪だ
バカだよ！
You're an idiot!
But I, as your friend,
will accept what you did.
でも 俺は仲間として
レナのやったことを受け入れる
（圭一）
これしか どうしようもなくて―
I'll accept this was the very, very
last thing you could've done...
悩み抜いたうえで至った最後の―
...after grappling
with it for so long.
最後の手段だったってことを
受け入れる
That's why I'll try
to understand you.
だから
俺は レナを理解しようと思う
We are the only ones who know
about these gruesome bags.
（圭一）このヤバイ袋の山を
知ったのは俺たちだけだ
俺たち全員が秘密にすれば
それで おしまいだ
If we all keep it
a secret, then it's over.
レナは何も気にすることはない
There's nothing for
you to worry about.
レナ！
Rena!
Mi.
Rika-chan.
（ﾚﾅ）梨花ちゃん…
沙都子！
Satoko.
Rika and I both lost our
parents and were alone...
私も梨花も両親を失って
独りぼっちですけれど―
今日まで それを
嘆いたことはありませんでしてよ
...but we never grieved over it.
That's because we had
friends who were like a family.
（沙都子）皆さんという…
仲間という名の家族がいたから
Friends like a family, huh?
“仲間という名の家族”か…
That's a good analogy for you.
沙都子にしちゃ いい例えだな
（梨花）み～！
I thought it was
the club leader's duty...
（魅音）
仲間の大切さを語るのは―
部長である私の役目だと
思っていただけに…
...to share the value of friendship.
Well...
いやはや 私も
部長失格かなぁなんて ナハハッ…
I guess I didn't
do so well as a club leader.
魅音…
Mion...
ごめん ふざけたね
I'm sorry. I shouldn't act silly.
I'm embarrassed I wasn't
able to understand...
（魅音）レナの境遇を
察しなかったことを―
...your situation as
your friend and club leader.
仲間として… 部長として恥じるよ
許してほしい
Please forgive me.
（魅音）もちろん レナが私たちに
相談しなかったことも許すよ
Of course, I'll forgive the fact
that you didn't consult us.
それは 私たちが―
That means we weren't worthy
to have things disclosed to us.
打ち明けるに足る存在じゃ
なかったってことだからね
We are responsible
for our immaturity.
その未熟さは 私たちの責任
That's why I won't blame you.
だから 私はレナを責めない
レナは人殺しだよ
I'm a murderer.
I bet I'll trouble you all.
きっと みんなに迷惑かけるよ
This isn't a dream or illusion.
夢とか幻とかじゃない
Plus, it's not even too late.
（圭一）
ましてや 手遅れでも何でもない
You still have options
to choose from.
レナには
まだ選べる選択肢が残ってるんだ
だから 選べ！
間に合う！ 来るんだ！
So choose!
There's still time! Come on!
Hey, Rena.
おい レナ！
あっ… あっ ごめん
- Sorry.
- Rena...
レナ 今日は帰ったら ゆっくり休め
When you go home,
take a nice rest.
Yeah.
うん ありがとう そうするね
Thank you.
I think I will.
（魅音）
レナ 自分を責めちゃダメだからね
Rena, don't blame
yourself, okay?
（ﾚﾅ）フフッ… やっぱり
みんなの言うとおりだったよ
It was just as everyone said.
（圭一）何がだ？
What was?
（ﾚﾅ）やっぱり
私 自分をダマせてなんかなかった
That I...
I wasn't able to fool myself.
No matter how hard I tried
to glorify my actions...
どう自分の行為を美化したって
私は心の中で―
...I was frightened in my heart
that I had done a terrifying thing.
恐ろしいことをしたと
おびえていた
みんなに助けてもらって
ここまで来て こんななんだもん
Since everyone helped me,
I was able to come this far.
もし みんなと会わずに
１人で全てを片づけていたら―
If I hadn't met everyone and
tried to clean it all up by myself...
私は十字架の重さに耐えきれず
つぶされてしまったかもしれない
...then I wouldn't have been
able to bear this cross...
...and been crushed by its weight.
（魅音）あしたからなんだけどさ…
Starting tomorrow...
I think it's best for
everyone to forget about today...
みんな そろって 今日のことを
忘れるのがいいと思うんだけど
どう思う？
（沙都子）そうですわね
...but what do you guys think?
I agree.
それが いちばん レナさんにとって
優しいことになると思いますわ
I think that's the kindest
thing we can do for Rena-san.
Rena is a strong person.
レナは強い人です
ボクたちが そう振る舞えば―
If we act that way,
then Rena will do the same.
レナも
そう振る舞ってくれますですよ
They say that if we continue
to act a certain way...
振る舞いも ずっと続けてれば
本当になるっていうもんな
...then it will soon
become the truth.
By not talking about it,
we'll eventually forget about it.
語らないことで そのうち
私たちは忘れていくよ
And our goal will be
to forget about it completely.
そして 完全に忘れきったときが
私たちのゴールだね
That day may or may
not come within our lifetime.
（梨花）恐らく その日は―
一生かけても 来るか来ないか
分からないと思いますが…
That might be true.
（沙都子）そうかもしれませんわね
あっ お～い！
Hey!
You're late! Rena!
遅いぞ レナ！
Sorry, sorry.
（ﾚﾅ）ごめん ごめん！
Okay, where shall we begin?
（圭一）ほんじゃ
まずは どっから行こうか？
（沙都子）
私 おなかがすきましたわ
- I'm hungry.
- Mi.
（梨花）み～！
（魅音）じゃ 焼きそば！
- Then yakisoba!
- Sounds good!
（ﾚﾅ）いいねえ！
（圭一）よっしゃ！
All right!
（大石(おおいし)）フッ…
To get my happiness,
I had done everything...
...but had done nothing
to be blamed and accused of.
The sound of footsteps
became louder every day.
Then I noticed the fact
there was no time.
I was a believer in life,
to be myself always.
And was asking
whether I would be alive.
Give me a reason
why not to adopt in this way.
Or judge me to be guilty
of so many incurable sins.
Tell me why or why not?
Complaining way too much.
Maybe I overlooked
something fatal for me.
Preview
Where I started to run
is the usual way home.
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
走りだしたのは いつもの帰り道
うごめくのは 不幸からの知らせ
What squirms is
the message from misfortune.
What is opened
is the deceptive scrap.
開かれるのは 惑わしのスクラップ
When They Cry.
「ひぐらしのなく頃に」
"Atonement" Chapter,
Episode 3: DOCUMENT 34.
- "Atonement" Chapter -
Episode 03: DOCUMENT 34
"Atonement" Chapter,
Episode 3: DOCUMENT 34.
Can you believe it?
あなたは信じられますか？